The amendment
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): that I offered, Blumenthal 4255, will not be made pending. But I want to emphasize the importance of the amendment and hope that I can work
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): with my colleagues on the substance of it, because it is so profoundly important to fairness
in the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): workplace and protection of American workers.
My
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): friend and colleague, the senator from Washington, Patty Murray, has spoken on this issue within the last few minutes,
and
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): I joined her in supporting the critical executive order issued by the president called the Fair Pay and Safe Workplaces Executive Order. This effort requires companies doing business by the federal government to disclose
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): whether they violated
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): any of the 14 longstanding labor laws protecting American workers included in this executive
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): order. There's no requirement to disclose a mere allegation or a claim of a violation of one of those laws. Rather, the executive order requires, very simply, disclosure of a determination by a court or administrative body of an actual
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): violation. This executive order, in effect, would be gutted by the National Defense Authorization Act now on
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the floor of this Congress. And the amendment that I was intending to offer is the very same amendment that was offered in the NDA markup, supported by groups like Easter Seals and Paralyzed Veterans of America
who worry
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that this language, in this law that we now have before us, will do a damaging injustice to our veterans and constituents with disabilities
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and thousands of other employees working under federal contracts. And I'm proud to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): be joined in this effort by not only Senator Murray, but also Senators Franken, Gillibrand, Brown, Sanders,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Lahey, Baldwin, Merkley, Boxer, Casey,
and
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the ranking member of the committee with jurisdiction over this bill, Senator Jack Reed of the Armed Services Committee, where the presiding officer
and I sit. We
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): really need to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): ensure that this
executive order,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the Fair Pay and Safe Workplaces
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): executive order, applies across all federal agencies,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): to all
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): workers, as many as possible at least, strengthening this vital effort to protect them, workers, and taxpayer dollars. It's not only about workers,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): it's also about taxpayer dollars. The laws that are covered here are sort of the bread-and-butter protections
of
all
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): federal workers and all workers generally, like the Americans with
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Disabilities Act, the Family and Medical Leave Act, and the Civil Rights
Act. Other
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): laws may
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): be more obscure, also covered, but they've been around for decades. And this measure and those laws are designed to protect
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): veterans and women from harmful, debilitating discrimination, among other
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): wrongful practices.
Let's be very
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): clear. Most companies
covered by
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): federal contracts, played by the rules, they obey the law.
All they
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): would need to do is literally check a box, confirming that they are in compliance. No big administrative expense, no elaborate bureaucratic hurdles to overcome. Check a box that there has been
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): compliance and the law is
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): fulfilled. For a small subset of companies with compliance
issues, the
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): contracting agency would take information about violations into consideration in the procurement process. Not to bar them--
they can
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): still be considered-- but they would then try to work with the company to make sure it comes into compliance
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): The basic theory of this executive order is a matter of
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): common sense. It's not about blacklisting companies, it's about ensuring that companies that want to do business with the federal government follow the law and provide a safe, equitable, fair workplace. And...
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Companies that violate those laws should not receive taxpayer dollars. Those are the companies we can trust to be partners in carrying out the federal government's work if they obey the law and they are in compliance with it. Companies that violate the law, very bluntly, are creating an unlevel playing field,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): forcing law-abiding companies
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): into an unfair competition for contracts. They can cut corners,
save
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): money by, in effect, skirting
the law,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and present low-ball offers, and when they
are hired
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): provide
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): poor performance. Again, to the detriment of taxpayers and wasting federal funds.
And,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): of course, it's not just about
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): dollars, the important to taxpayers, but about workers. Every year, tens of thousands of American workers
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): are denied overtime wages, unlawfully discriminated against in hiring and pay. They have their health and safety put at risk by federal contractors who cut those corners on workers' safety or otherwise deny a basic, safe workplace. And...
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): That's another reason that we need full force and effect to this executive order, not the gutting
of it
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that is contained now in the NDAA before us. Some have called the fair pay executive order one of the most important advances for workers achieved by this administration.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): it is. According to the Department of Labor, one in five Americans are employed by companies that do business with the federal government, an enormous source of leverage requiring compliance with federal protections, not just in letter, but in spirit. We must very simply allow for consistent and appropriate
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): application of this executive order to ensure that
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): workers for contractors under the defense laws have the same protections as other
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): workers. And the NDAA provision that guts this executive order must be removed at some point. It may not happen
in our
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): considering of this measure now.
But
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): my hope is that we can work with colleagues and overcome the potentially harmful effects of this provision. I look forward, in fact, to a collegial effort to make sure that we provide long-term protection to American workers through this executive order.
Thank you,
Speaker 3: Mr. President, and
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): I yield the floor.